welcome back to APUSH at under 3 minutes
no time for intros let's get into it so
the Second Great Awakening what is it
short answer it was a religious revival
but more than that it was a massive
cultural shift that reshaped American
society and politics so you might be
wondering what caused the second gr
Awakening well a few things first was
the rise of democratic and
individualistic beliefs second was a
response to rationalism because of
criticism of the Enlightenment being too
rational based and let's not forget the
market Revolution which uprooted
communities and made people more mobile
creating new opportun ities for
religious movements to spread here's
some examples of parts of this movement
camp meetings became huge social events
especially on the frontier creatures
like Charles G fidley LED emotional Fury
revivals in places like the burned over
District of New York where religious
enthusiasm Ran So High it was said that
there was no one left to convert the
Second Great Awakening also sparked
major reform movements religious leaders
preached that individuals could Achieve
Personal salvation and improveed Society
this inspired people to tackle issues
like abolitionism Temperance and women's
rights jeren Lee and Harry hoer hoer
haer we'll go with hoer two prominent
African-American preachers challenged
traditional ideas by showing that black
Americans and women could lead in
spiritual life and one more thing new
religious movements emerged Joseph Smith
founded the Church of Jesus Christ of
latterday Saints or Mormons while
William Miller's predictions about the
end of the world led to the formation of
the Adventist churches here are your AP
style questions for this topic pause
now I'll put the answers on the screen
now I will see you in the next one